elisa.filevich@uni-tuebingen.de

## Elisa Filevich

Junior Group Leader <a href="http://metamotorlab.filevich.com">http://metamotorlab.filevich.com</a>

Hector Research Institute of Education Sciences and Psychology Eberhard Karls Universität Tübingen, Germany. Europastraße 6, 72072 Tübingen, Germany Tel +49 30 2093 6313

## **Personal Information**

Nationality: Argentinian Date of Birth: 23.08.1983

Marital status: Married, two children, born 2017 and 2021.

## **Research Profile**

I am a cognitive neuroscientist investigating the neural correlates of consciousness. I focus on different aspects of motor awareness and subjective experiences associated with it: the awareness of intentions (volition), the awareness of control (agency) and motor experience (motor metacognition).

## **Academic Appointments**

03/2023 - now	Junior Group Leader - Funded by "Freigeist" Fellowship Hector Research Institute of Education Sciences and Psychology Eberhard Karls Universität Tübingen, Germany.
2017 – 2023	Junior Group Leader - Funded by "Freigeist" Fellowship Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience and Institute of Psychology, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, Germany.
2015 – 2017	Scientific employee (Seminar instructor) Faculty of Sports Sciences, Leipzig University, Germany. Guest Researcher Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin, Germany.
2012 – 2015	Postdoctoral fellow. Structural Plasticity group Max Planck Institute, Berlin, Germany Team Leader: Dr. Simone Kühn

# **Education and Training**

Education and Training		
2008 – 2012	PhD. Institute of Cognitive Neuroscience. Intentional inhibition and human voluntary action. University College London. UK Advisor: Prof. Patrick Haggard	
2012	Visiting Scholar. Consciousness and Computation Laboratory Columbia University, NY, USA Advisor: Asst. Prof. Hakwan Lau	
2005 – 2007	Undergraduate researcher. Laboratory of Molecular and Cellular Biology (LBMC). University of Buenos Aires, Argentina Advisor: Prof. Osvaldo D. Uchitel	
2005	Undergraduate researcher. Biochemistry and Molecular Biology. Colorado State University, CO, USA Advisor: Prof. James Bamburg	
2001 – 2007	Licenciatura (equivalent to German "Diplom") in Biological Sciences. University of Buenos Aires, Argentina. Final grade: 8.6/10	

### **Preprints**

2023

Charalampaki, A., Ciston, A.B., **Filevich, E.** Contributions of tactile information to the sense of agency and its metacognitive representations. BioRxiv 2023.12.15.571840; doi: https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.12.15.571840

Chancel, M., **Filevich, E.**, & Faivre, N. (2023, April 4). Exogenous and endogenous sources of uncertainty inform global performance monitoring. PsvArXiv. https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/gbjy5

### **Publications in Peer-Reviewed Journals**

\* Indicates equal contributions

2023

Prior information differentially affects discrimination decisions and subjective confidence reports.

Constant, M., Pereira, M., Faivre, N., & Filevich, E.

Nat Commun 14, 5473 (2023).

Impaired Metacognition of Voluntary Movement in Functional Movement Disorder. Verrel, J., Chwolka, F., **Filevich, E.**, Moyé, J., Paulus, T., Zittel, S., Bäumer, T., Münchau, A. and Weissbach, A.

Mov Disord, 38: 435-443.

Motor outcomes congruent with intentions may sharpen metacognitive representations. Charalampaki, A., Peters, C., Maurer, H., Maurer, L.K., Müller, H., Verrel, J., **Filevich, E.** 

Cognition, 235, 105388.

2022

Metacognitive domains are not aligned along a dimension of internal-external information source.

Arbuzova, P., Maurer, L.K. & Filevich, E.

Psychon Bull Rev (2022).

Metacognitive improvement: Disentangling adaptive training from experimental confounds.

Rouy, M. de Gardelle, V., Reyes, G., Sackur, J., Vergnaud, J.C., **Filevich, E.\***, Faivre, N\*.

Journal of Experimental Psychology: General, 151(9), 2083–2091.

Consensus Goals in the Field of Visual Metacognition.

Rahnev, D., Balsdon, T., Charles, L., de Gardelle, V., Denison, R., Desender, K., Faivre, N., **Filevich, E.**, Fleming, S. M., Jehee, J., Lau, H., Lee, A. L. F., Locke, S. M., Mamassian, P., Odegaard, B., Peters, M., Reyes, G., Rouault, M., Sackur, J., ... Zylberberg, A.

Perspectives on Psychological Science 17(6), 1746-1765.

No evidence of impaired visual and tactile metacognition in adults with tourette disorder.

Arbuzova, P., Guo, S., Koß, C., Kurvits, L., Faivre, N., Kühn, A. A., **Filevich, E.**, & Ganos, C.

Parkinsonism & Related Disorders, 97, 29–33.

Spent time outdoors for your brain: An in-depth longitudinal MRI study. Kühn, S., Mascherek, A., **Filevich, E.**, Lisofsky, N., Becker, M., Butler, O., et al. The World Journal of Biological Psychiatry. *The World Journal of Biological Psychiatry*, 23(3), 201-207

Judgments of agency are affected by sensory noise without recruiting metacognitive processing.

Constant, M., Salomon, R., Filevich, E.

eLife 11:e72356

2021

Measuring metacognition of direct and indirect parameters of voluntary movement.

Arbuzova, P., Peters, C., Roed, L., Koss, C., Maurer, H., Maurer, L. K., Mueller, H., Verrel, J., & Filevich, E.

Journal of Experimental Psychology: General, 150(11), 2208-2229.

2020

Response-related signals increase confidence but not metacognitive performance.

**Filevich, E.**, Koß, C., & Faivre, N. eNeuro 7(3) eneuro.0326-19.2020.

I know that I know nothing: Cortical thickness and functional connectivity underlying meta-ignorance ability in pre-schoolers.

**Filevich**, E., Forlim, C. G., Fehrman, C., Forster, C., Paulus, M., Shing, Y. L., & Kühn, S. (2020).

Developmental Cognitive Neuroscience, 41, 100738.

The Confidence Database.

Rahnev, D., Desender, K., Lee, A.L.F., Adler, W.T., Aguilar-Lleyda, D., Akdoğan, B., ..., Filevich, E.,.... Zylberberg, A. (2020)

Nat Hum Behav. 4, 317-325

2019

Identifying predictors of within-person variance in MRI-based brain volume estimates.

Karch, J. D., **Filevich, E.**, Wenger, E., Lisofsky, N., Becker, M., Butler, O., ... Kühn, S. (2019).

Neurolmage, 200, 575-589.

2018

Behavioural, modeling, and electrophysiological evidence for domain-generality in human metacognition.

Faivre, N., Filevich, E., Solovey, G., Kühn, S., Blanke, O.

The Journal of Neuroscience, 0322-17.

2017

Within-person adaptivity in frugal judgments from memory.

Filevich, E.\*, Horn, S. S\*., & Kühn, S. Psychological Research 83 (3), 613-630

Day2day: Investigating daily variability of magnetic resonance imaging measures over half a year.

**Filevich E.\***, Lisofsky, N.\*, Becker, M., Butler, O., Lochstet, M., Martensson, J., Wenger, E., Lindenberger, U. and Kühn, S.

BMC Neuroscience, 18:65.

Resting-state fMRI correlations: from link-wise unreliability to whole brain stability. Pannunzi, M., Hindriks, R., Bettinardi, R. G., Wenger, E., Lisofsky, N., Martensson, J., Butler, O., **Filevich, E**., Becker, M., Lochstet, M., Kühn S., Deco, G. *NeuroImage* 157:250-262

Seeing double: Exploring the phenomenology of self-reported absence of rivalry in bistable pictures. **Filevich, E.**, Becker, M., Wu, YH. & Kühn, S. *Frontiers in Human Neuroscience* 11:301.

2015

"Just another tool for online studies" (JATOS): An easy solution for setup and management of web servers supporting online studies.

Lange, K., Kühn, S., Filevich, E.

PLoS one, 10(6).

Metacognitive mechanisms underlying lucid dreaming.

Filevich, E., Dresler, M., Brick, T. R., & Kühn, S.

The Journal of Neuroscience, 35(3), 1082–1088.

2013

Brain correlates of subjective freedom of choice.

Filevich, E., Vanneste, P., Brass, M., Fias, W., Haggard, P. Kühn, S.

Consciousness and Cognition 22 (4), 1271-1284

Persistence of internal representations of alternative voluntary actions.

**Filevich, E.**, & Haggard, P. *Frontiers in Cognition*, 4: 202.

There is no free won't: Antecedent brain activity predicts decisions to inhibit.

Filevich, E., Kühn, S., & Haggard, P.

PLoS one, 8(2), e53053.

2012

Grin and bear it! Neural consequences of a voluntary decision to act or inhibit action. **Filevich, E.**, Haggard, P.

Experimental Brain Research, 223(3), 341-351.

Negative Motor Phenomena in cortical stimulation: implications for inhibitory control of human action.

Filevich, E., Kühn, S., Haggard, P.

Cortex 48(10), 1251-1261

Intentional inhibition in human action: The power of "no."

Filevich, E.\*, Kühn, S.\*, Haggard, P.

Neuroscience and Biobehavioral Reviews, 36(4), 1107-1118.

### **Book Chapters**

2014

What is the human sense of agency, and is it metacognitive?

Chambon, V. Filevich, E. Haggard, P. In Stephen M. Fleming and Chris Frith (Eds).

The cognitive neuroscience of metacognition. Springer

2012

Psychogenic Movement Disorders and Other Conversion Disorders.

**Filevich, E.** Haggard, P. Components of voluntary action. In Hallett, M., Lang, A. E., Jankovic, J., Fahn, S., Halligan, P. W., Voon, V., & Cloninger, C. R. (Eds.).

Cambridge University Press.

#### **Dissertation**

2013

Volition and inhibition: Objective and subjective aspects of human volitional control. **Filevich, E.** Doctoral thesis, UCL (University College London). https://discovery.ucl.ac.uk/id/eprint/1383056/

### **Invited Talks**

2024

**Meta-Ed workshop on metacognition and education.** "Come together": Motor metacognition in music learning.

2023

Cognitive Sciences Colloqium. University of Tübingen, Department of Computer Science. Measuring subjective experience (properly, we hope): Investigating metacognition of motor imagery.

Metacognition and Consciousness Workshop, Marseille, France. Metacognition of motor imagery.

1st European Summer School in Sensory Neuroscience (ESSSN 2023). (Online) Measuring subjective experience.

New Ideas in Volition. One-day workshop organised by the Berlin School of Mind and Brain. Metacognition of Agency.

2022 Women in Cognitive Science Seminar Series, Universidad del Desarrollo, Santiago, Chile. (Online) How (much) do we know about the way we move our bodies?: Motor metacognition and its relationship to other metacognitive domains 2021 Perception & Action Seminar Series. Cognitive, Linguistic, and Psychological Sciences department at Brown University. (Online) How (much) do we know about the way we move our bodies?: Motor metacognition and its relationship to other metacognitive domains Perceptual Confidence and Uncertainty workshop, Paris (Online). Are judgments of agency metacognitive? Consciousness Club, FIL. (Online) Motor Metacognition and agency. Talk recording available at http://metacoglab.org/consciousness-club-events/ 2021/1/27/elisa-filevich 2020 Copenhagen Cognition, Intention, and Action Group, University of Copenhagen. (Online Workshop) Motor metacognition and agency LPC Lab Seminar, Aix-Marseille Université. Motor Metacognition: How much does our brain know about the way it moves the body? Rahnev lab, Georgia Tech, School of Psychology. (Online) Motor metacognition: How does our brain know how our body moves? 2019 Workshop on Metacognition. Laboratoire de Psychologie et NeuroCognition (LPNC), Grenoble, France. Motor metacognition: How does our brain know how our body moves? Freie Universität Berlin - CCNB Seminar Series. Germany. Relationships between domains of metacognitive monitoring 2018 Department of Experimental Psychology (Zangwill Club), Cambridge University, UK. Metacognition of internally generated processes 2017 Geneva University (Brain and Cognition Seminar), Switzerland. Metacognition of internally generated processes Experimental Psychology Society (EPS) Meeting, Belfast, UK. Domaingenerality in perceptual metacognition 2014 Department of Psychology, Lund University, Sweden. What we can learn from introspection

# Presentations in Conferences (first author only)

2023	<b>Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness (ASSC26)</b> , New York City, USA. Different metacognitive paradigms.
2020	Argentine Society for Neuroscience Research (SAN), Argentina. Symposium - Open Neuroscience: new approaches for new tools. "Just Another Tool for Online Studies": An open-source tool to conduct cognitive science experiments online.
2019	Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness (ASSC23), London, Canada. Metacognitive access to high- and low-level aspects of motor control. (Plenary Symposium)
2018	Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness (ASSC22), Cracow, Poland. The brain basis of meta-ignorance in pre-schoolers
2017	Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness (ASSC21), Beijing, China. Metacognition of movement: the case of facial expressions.

2014 Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness (ASSC19), Brisbane, Australia. Lucid dreaming, introspection and awareness of mind-wandering:

behavioural and brain bases

Organization for Human Brain Mapping (OHBM), Hamburg, Germany. Faces and houses perceived simultaneously in monocular rivalry images: fMRI evidence

2012 Society for Neuroscience (SfN), New Orleans, USA. There is no free won't: antecedecent brain activity predicts decisions to inhibit

> Association for the Scientific Study of Consciousness (ASSC16), Brighton, UK. Brain correlates of subjective freedom of choice

## Workshops Led

2020 Running experiments online. 2.5 hours, Berlin School of Mind and Brain and Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience.

Running web-based experiments in consciousness research. 3 hours,

Association for the Scientific Study (ASSC23), London, Canada.

2018 Running experiments online with JATOS. 2.5 hours, MRC-Cognition and Brain

Unit, Cambridge University, UK.

2016 Running experiments online with JATOS. 5 hours, Graduate School for Mind

and Brain, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, Germany

### Teaching

2019

2019 Seminar series: Neural Bases of Metacognition. MSc, Berlin School of Mind

and Brain. Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin. Course size: 9 students. Mean overall

student rating: 5.11 (Minimum: 1 - Maximum: 6).

2018 - now Contribution to lecture series. Neural bases of metacognition. MSc course

> "Models of Neural Systems", Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience. Course size: ca. 30 students. Latest mean overall student rating: 1.8 (Minimum: 5

- Maximum: 1).

Contribution to lecture series ("Ringvorlesung"). Neural bases of

metacognition. BSc, Institute for Psychology, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin.

2015 - 2016 Seminar Instructor, Sport Psychology. Leipzig University, Germany.

2010 Laboratory demonstrator, First year Psychology. University College London,

UK.

# **Student Supervision and Evaluation**

2017 - now Supervision of PhD projects. Completed: 1 - Ongoing: 3

2018 - now **Secondary supervision of PhD projects.** Total to date (ongoing): 5

2019 - now Member of PhD thesis committee. Total to date: 4

2019 - now Supervision of MSc theses projects. Total to date: 5

2018 - now Supervision of 8-week rotation projects. Total to date: 11

2010 - 2011 Informal supervision of 3-months projects for an MSc in Neuroscience

course. Total: 3

### Mentoring

2022 Mental Health and Early Career Researchers - Panel Discussion - Scholar

Minds Berlin

2022 Growing Up In Science Talk - Scholar Minds Berlin

2021-2022 Mentor within the WiNS (Women in Natural Sciences) program

### Ad-hoc Reviewing

## 2011 – now Scientific Journals

Behavior Research Methods; Brain; Brain and Neuroscience Advances; Cognition; Consciousness & Cognition; Cortex; eLife; Experimental Brain Research; Frontiers in Consciousness Research; Journal of Neurophysiology; Journal of Neuroscience; Nature Communications; Nature Communications Psychology; Neuroimage; Neuropsychologia; Neuroscience and Biobehavioural Reviews; Neuroscience of Consciousness; PLoS one; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences (PNAS); Psychology of Consciousness: Theory, Research, and Practice; Psychonomic Bulletin and Review; npj Science of Learning; Scientific Reports; Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience (SCAN), Trends in Cognitive

Sciences.

2019 – now Funding agencies

Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG)

Wellcome Trust, UK

National Science Center Poland (NCN)

Klaus-Tschira Boost fund - German Scholars Organization

Agence Nationale de la Recherche (ANR - France)

2019 – now Member of PhD Thesis Evaluation Committee

Total to date: 4

## **Other Contributions**

2022 Growing Up In Science Talk - Scholar Minds Berlin

2019 - now Metacognition Working group leader in the Neural Architecture of

Consciousness consortium. 15 active members (https://neuralarchcon.org/).

2019 Member of Scientific Committee – Association for the Scientific Study of

Consciousness (ASSC)

**2017 – now Member of ProFiL Network.** Professional network, training and coaching for

women in natural and social sciences working in universities in Berlin.

**2014 – now** Software development. Active development of an open-source software tool to

run experiments online. www.jatos.org

### **Additional Professional Training**

2018 Workshop series from Wissenschaftsmanagement (ZWM): "Professionals

in Science". Included Communication and Conflict Management; Conducting

Interviews; Research Project Management; Leadership.

2018 Workshop series from the ProFiL program (TU Berlin). Included Career

Planning; Faculty Hiring Procedures in Germany and Abroad; Leadership;

Academic Self-management; Writing Grant Applications.

**Public Engagement** 

**2023** Gespräch unter Bäumen, xHain Hacker space. "Measuring subjective

experience properly. We hope." Scientific presentation and discussion.

**2022** Berlin Brains series. Urania Berlin, Germany. "Can you raise your left eyebrow?"

Science outreach event.

https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=def7O0judvg

**2015** The Long Night of the Sciences. Berlin, Germany ("Lange Nacht der

Wissenschaften") - Science outreach event.

**2007** The Basement of Perception - Cognitive science outreach event.

Museum of Natural History, Buenos Aires, Argentina.

### Awards, Fellowships, and Research Grants

**2023** Freigeist Fellowship - Second Funding Period. "'Come together': Bridging

Education Research and Cognitive Neuroscience by Investigating Motor Metacognition in Music Learning" VolkswagenStiftung, Germany. 479,230 €

Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions - Doctoral Networks (DN) grant. "CODE (COnfident DEcisions)". European Commission. 2023. Funding for PhD training within a European consortium. Led by Prof. Janneke Jehee. Over 2.5 M€. My role:

One of the ten fellows of the consortium.

**2018** Research Training Group (RTG). Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) RTG

2386 "Extrospection: External Acces to Higher Cognitive Processes". Role: Principal Investigator. Total funding for the cluster of ten Principal Investigators:

over 1,530,000 €

**2016** Freigeist Fellowship. "Metacognition of action: behavioural and brain bases"

VolkswagenStiftung, Germany. Grant number 91620, 5 years, 919,800 €

**2008** Four-year PhD Studentship in Neuroscience. "Inhibitory processes in human

voluntary action." Wellcome Trust, UK. Grant number 086123/Z/08/Z, 4 years,

over 148,000 GBP

2008 Overseas Research Scholarships (ORS). Higher Education Funding Council for

England (HEFCE). Funding to cover the difference between Overseas and UK/EU

tuition fees.

**2006** Undergraduate scholarship. ("Beca estímulo") University of Buenos Aires,

Argentina.

Languages

German C1 (approximate level)

**English** Fluent

Spanish Native